Let's talk about exceptions. We've seen exceptions quite a bit over the course of
this class. We've seen type error, syntax error, value error, indentation error,
but we haven't really figured out what to do about them. We saw some simple
tri-excepts yesterday, but that doesn't really, that's not enough in the course of
a more complex program. So I'm going to tell you a little bit about the
exception hierarchy about raising exceptions and about how to use try catch and
how to create our own custom exception classes. So a little bit about exceptions.
The built-in exceptions, they're an exception handling. It's a really nice
feature of Python. Those syntax errors that we've seen, they do a pretty good job of
telling us what went wrong, right? If we get an indentation error, we know that
we didn't indent our code properly. If we get a value error, that means that something
is wrong with the input that we gave. Even if the syntax is totally correct,
sometimes errors occur when your program is wrong. For example, if you tried to run our
final exercise from introduction to Python and you didn't have a valid
internet connection, it would just raise an exception that we didn't catch and
exit the program. So even if your syntax is 100% correct, your program can still have
exceptions. Unhandled exceptions are fatal to your program. It's going to print
out a trace back and then quit your code wherever it was at that time. So
and it'll stop your interpreter, it'll exit your program. So like for
production code, having uncold exceptions is pretty bad, right? Just take
down your website, depending on what you're seeing or for using a web server,
your end user will see a 500 error and that's not very good, right?
But once you learn a little bit more about these exceptions and about how to handle
them, it'll help you write apps that are a lot more robust in the face of issues.
So some common types of exceptions that you might see, there are a few more in the Python
documentation, but very quickly attribute error if I tried to use an attribute name that
wasn't on my instance, I would get this error, import error if I tried to import something
that wasn't found. Key error, we've seen this one if key was not an
introduction error, syntax error, the parser just doesn't even know what to do with your file,
indentation error, if you're messing with the level of indentation for if statements,
classes, et cetera, functions where you need to have your first line of code
indented one level. And this keyboard interrupt error, that's an interesting one.
So for those of you who've been seeing me use the rubble, you've seen me hit maybe control
C. If I'm typing something and I'm like, oh, I made a mistake, I don't want to hit
and turn get a syntax error, I know that this isn't valid code, I could hit control C,
it doesn't run my code, and in this case, it generates a keyboard interrupt error.
So for programs that you run on the command line, if it's taking a really long time,
I've been writing pretty fast scripts, you want to exit out of it, you can hit control C,
it'll generate a keyboard error and it'll quit your program while it's running.
Just a quick thing about this keyboard interrupt error, let me take a look at the Python documentation here.
So these built in exceptions, we'll see that there's an exception base class,
and all of the exceptions mostly use this base class in terms of their object hierarchy.
We and our program code don't want to do that.
If we're going to be handling exceptions, we always want to handle types that are of exception exception,
never base exception.
Exception here is one of the subclasses of base exception.
If we catch base exception, we're going to also catch those keyboard interrupt errors.
So you know, someone will be running your script, press control C, and it won't do anything,
and they're going to get pretty mad at you.
So remember that, don't catch base exception, catch exception and start.